Finding Aid for Herbert Orin Crisler papers 1922-1978
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
H. O. Crisler papers 1922-1978
Crisler, H. O. (Herbert Orin), 1899-1982.
2 film reels
1 oversize folders
7 oversize volumes
8 linear feet
Football coach, 1938-1948, and Athletic Director at the University of Michigan, 1941-1968. Papers include correspondence and other papers concerning his career at the University of Chicago, the University of Minnesota, Princeton University, and the University of Michigan; materials concerning his work and association with the National Collegiate Athletic Association rules committee, 1942-1977, the Intercollegiate (Big Ten) Conference, and the University's Board in Control of Intercollegiate Activities; also include materials relating to University of Chicago football coach, Amos Alonzo Stagg, Ralph Young, athletic director at Michigan State University, and the founding and first years of the American Football League; and photographs.
85823 AC UAm Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The papers were donated by Crisler in 1979 and 1980. Donor No. 6327
The collection is open for research.
Herbert Orin (Fritz) Crisler was born in Earlville, Illinois on January 12, 1899. After graduating from high school, Crisler enrolled in the University of Chicago, where he participated in three sports: baseball, basketball, and football, and where he became an All-American on the Chicago football team coached by Amos Alonzo Stagg. Crisler's studies were interrupted in 1918 for a brief period of military service, largely spent at the Officers Training School at Waco, Texas. Crisler received his Bachelor of Arts degree in 1922. Following graduation, Crisler was offered a position with Chicago's athletic department. At various times over the next eight years he coached Chicago's baseball, basketball, and football teams. In April, 1923 Crisler married Dorothy Adams.
Crisler left the University of Chicago in 1930 to become athletic director and head football coach at the University of Minnesota. His stay at Minnesota was a short one. In 1932 he was appointed head football coach at Princeton University. Crisler remained at Princeton until 1938 when he began his long association with The University of Michigan.
From 1938 to 1948 Crisler served as Michigan's head football coach, replacing Harry Kipke. In his ten years as head coach at Michigan, Crisler compiled a 73-16-3 record, winning two Big Ten championships and culminating his career with an undefeated season in 1947 and being voted National Champion following a 47-0 victory over Southern California in the 1948 Rose Bowl. In 1941, Crisler took on additional duties, succeeding Fielding H. Yost as athletic director. Crisler remained at the helm of Michigan's athletic program until 1968. Following Crisler's retirement, Don Canham became Michigan's Athletic Director.
In addition to his coaching activities Crisler was active on the NCAA (National Collegiate Athletic Association) Rules Committee. This committee is responsible for establishing the rules under which collegiate football is played. The committee meets annually to revise the official NCAA rule book. Crisler chaired the committee from 1950 to 1958, and became the second individual to be appointed a lifetime member of the committee (Amos Alonzo Stagg was the first).
Crisler is the author of two books: Practical Football, published in 1933, and Modern Football, published in 1949.
Crisler died in 1982.
An overview of Crisler's career can be found in A legacy of champions: the story of the men who built University of Michigan football [Farmington Hills, MI.: CTC Productions & Sports; 1996].
The Crisler papers document Fritz Crisler's career in athletics, 1923-1978, as a student athlete at the University of Chicago, football coach at Minnesota, Princeton and Michigan, as Athletic Director at Michigan and as a member of the NCAA football rules committee, 1942-1977. The collection is composed of several series: General and Topical Correspondence; Speeches and Articles; Football Material; NCAA Football Rules Committee; Intercollegiate Conference [Big Ten]; Clippings and Scrapbooks; Amos Alonzo Stagg; Photographs and films.
Subjects:
American Football League.; Athletics--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Football--United States.; Intercollegiate Conference of Faculty Representatives.; Michigan State University.; National Collegiate Athletic Association.; Stagg, Amos Alonzo, 1862-1965.; University of Michigan--Sports.; University of Michigan. Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics.; University of Michigan--Football.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Crisler, H. O. (Herbert Orin), 1899-1982.; Football.; Japan.; Stagg, Amos Alonzo, 1862-1965.; University of Chicago.; University of Michigan--Football.; University of Minnesota.
Contributors:
Young, Ralph.
Genre/Form:
Motion pictures.; Photographs.
- General Correspondence 1925-1978
  The general correspondence, 1925-1978, primarily relates to Crisler's activities in collegiate football.
  - Undated (Box 1)
  - 1925-1939 (Box 1)
    (re. financial investments)
  - 1920, 1925 (Box 1)
  - 1930-1931 (Box 1)
  - 1932 (Box 1)
  - 1932 (Box 1)
    (containing student petitions and correspondence requesting Crisler to remain at the University of Minnesota)
  - 1933 (Box 1)
  - 1935 (Box 1)
  - 1936-1937 (Box 1)
  - 1938 undated, January-February 21, 1938 (Box 1)
  - February 22-23, 1938 (Box 1)
  - February 24-March 1, 1938 (Box 1)
  - 1939 (Box 1)
  - 1940-1949 (Box 1)
  - 1950-1959 (Box 1)
  - November 1955-January 1956, 2 folders (Box 1)
    (re. disturbance at the 1955 Michigan-Ohio State football game)
  - 1960-1967 (Box 1)
  - January-June 1968 (Box 1)
  - July-December 1968 (Box 1)
  - 1969 (Box 1)
  - 1970 (Box 1)
  - 1971 (Box 1)
  - 1972 (Box 1)
  - 1973-1974 (Box 1)
  - 1975 (Box 1)
  - 1976 (Box 1)
  - 1977 (Box 1)
  - 1978 (Box 1)
  - 1979 (Box 1)
- Topical Correspondence 1940-1966
  The topical correspondence contains a miscellanea of material, including two folders of "squawks" - crank mail dating from 1940 to 1957 and criticizing The University of Michigan's athletic program; correspondence with the University Health Service concerning athlete safety; correspondence regarding Crisler's involvement with the military during World War II: his abortive assignment in 1942 to the Great Lakes Training Station to direct its physical training and athletic programs, and in 1945, his supervision of sports clinics held in Panama; and correspondence with officials at Michigan State University, principally Ralph H. Young, that university's athletic director.
  - "Squawks, " 1940-1949 (Box 1)
  - "Squawks, " 1950-1957 (Box 1)
  - The UM Health Service 1942-1949 (Box 1)
  - World War 11 1942-1944 (Box 1)
  - Panama Sports Clinics October 1944-January 1946 (Box 1)
  - Mackey, (Frank) 1976-1977 (Box 1)
  - Michigan State University
    - 1940-1942 (Box 1)
    - 1943-1946 (Box 1)
    - 1947-1949 (Box 1)
    - 1950-1952 (Box 1)
    - 1953 (Box 1)
    - 1954-1960, 1965-1966 (Box 1)
    - Clippings and miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Speeches and Articles 1927-1969
  The Speeches and Articles series consist of transcripts of speeches given by Crisler, articles written by him, and a number of folders containing note cards and reference materials.
  - Undated (Box 2)
  - 1927-1947 (Box 2)
  - Transcript: "Should Football be Subsidized?" August 1948 (Box 2)
  - 1950-1951, 1969 (Box 2)
  - Notes, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Speech materials, 5 folders (Box 2)
  - Retirement speech for Crisler (Box 2)
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files series contains papers relating to the formation of the American Football League, including minutes of the League's first and second organizational meetings; scouting reports made by Crisler on Big Ten basketball teams between 1924 and 1930; lawsuits over athlete eligibility in which Crisler became involved; and papers concerning Crisler's work as a consultant on athletics to Saginaw Valley College in 1967.
  - American Football League
    - Correspondence 1959 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - University of Illinois "Slush Fund" Scandal 1967 (Box 2)
  - Crisler Scouting reports, Big Ten Basketball 1924-1930 (Box 2)
  - Porter Lawsuits 1971 re: eligibility (Box 2)
  - Jackson Lawsuit 1955-1968 re: eligibility (Box 2)
  - Saginaw Valley College 1987 (Box 2)
  - Tom Harmon's "Football Today" Magazine Correspondence 1976 (Box 2)
- Football Material, 1923-1947
  Crisler's papers contain a wealth of material from his coaching career and his long and active association with the NCAA Rules Committee. The football material includes coach's notebooks containing records of staff and squad meetings, field work, and notes and comments on actual games; plays and practice notes containing details of the football squad's daily practice sessions and play diagrams; and several topical files.
  - Plays and Practice
    - 1923, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1924 (Box 2)
    - 1925 (Box 2)
    - 1926 (Box 2)
    - 1927 (Box 2)
    - 1928 (Box 2)
    - 1929 (Box 2)
    - 1930
      - Coach's notebook 1930 (Box 2)
      - Plays and Practice 1930 (Box 2)
      - Scouting reports and game plans 1930 (Box 2)
    - 1931
      - Coach's notebook 1931 (Box 2)
      - Plays and Practice 1931, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Scouting reports and game plans 1931 (Box 2)
      - Spring Fall Tournament 1931 (Box 2)
    - 1932
      - Coach's notebook 1932 (Box 3)
      - Plays and Practice 1932 (Box 3)
      - Scouting reports and game plans 1932 (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous 1932 (Box 3)
    - 1933
      - Coach's notebook 1933 (Box 3)
      - Plays and practice 1933 (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - 1934 (Box 3)
    - 1935 (Box 3)
    - 1936 (Box 3)
    - 1937-1938 (Box 3)
    - 1938 Coach's practice notebook (Box 3)
    - 1938-1940 Scouting reports (Box 3)
    - 1939 Coach's practice notebook (Box 3)
    - 1939-1940 Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - 1940-1941 Miscellaneous play diagrams (Box 3)
    - 1941
      - Coach's practice notebook 1941 (Box 3)
      - Daily practice work sheets 1941 (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous 1941 (Box 3)
    - 1941-1943 Scouting reports (Box 3)
    - 1942 Daily practice work sheets (Box 3)
    - 1942-1944 Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - 1944-1947 Scouting reports (Box 3)
    - 1945 Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - 1946 Miscellaneous (Box 4)
  - Form letters mailed to football team candidates
    - 1927, 1930-1934 (Box 4)
    - 1933-1941 (Box 4)
    - 1938-1947 (Box 4)
  - University of Minnesota miscellaneous 1930-1931 (Box 4)
  - Princeton University miscellaneous 1932-1936 (Box 4)
  - University of Michigan miscellaneous 1940-1964 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous game charts, ca. 1932-1936 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous play diagrams, 6 folders (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous Game Charts (11) (Folder UAm)
- NCAA Football Rules Comm 1946-1977
  The records of the NCAA Rules Committee consist of correspondence, minutes of annual meetings, 1946 to 1975, and revised rule and rule interpretation booklets which have been annotated by Crisler.
  - Correspondence
    - 1946-1949, undated (Box 4)
    - 1950 (Box 4)
    - 1951-1953 (Box 4)
    - 1953, 2 folders (Box 4)
      [Free substitution rule]
    - 1954-1957 (Box 4)
    - January-March 1958 (Box 4)
    - April-June 1958 (Box 4)
    - July-December 1958 (Box 4)
    - 1959 (Box 4)
    - 1960 (Box 4)
    - 1961 (Box 4)
    - January-June 1962 (Box 4)
    - July-December 1962 (Box 5)
    - 1963 (Box 5)
    - 1964-1965 (Box 5)
    - 1966-1967 (Box 5)
    - 1968-1971 (Box 5)
    - 1972-1977 (Box 5)
  - Minutes
    - 1946-1949 (Box 5)
    - 1950-1954 (Box 5)
    - 1955-1959 (Box 5)
    - 1960-1964 (Box 5)
    - 1965 (Box 5)
    - 1966 (Box 5)
    - 1967 (Box 5)
    - 1968 (Box 5)
    - 1969 (Box 5)
    - 1970 (Box 5)
    - 1971 (Box 5)
    - 1972 (Box 5)
    - 1973 (Box 5)
    - 1974 (Box 5)
    - 1975 (Box 5)
  - NCAA Official Rules Handbook and related materials
    - 1942 (Box 5)
    - 1946 (Box 5)
    - 1947 (Box 5)
    - 1948 (Box 5)
    - 1948 proposed recodification, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - 1948 [draft of joint NCAA-National Federation of State High School Athletic Associations], 2 folders (Box 5)
    - 1967 (Box 6)
    - 1969 (Box 6)
    - 1970 (Box 6)
    - 1971 (Box 6)
    - 1972 (Box 6)
    - 1973 (Box 6)
    - 1974 (Box 6)
    - 1975 (Box 6)
    - 1976 (Box 6)
    - 1977 (Box 6)
    - 1979 (Box 6)
  - Bulletins 1949-1958 (Box 6)
  - Historical background (Box 6)
  - Joint NCAA-National Federation Football Code 1947-1948, 2 folders (Box 6)
    (Reports and miscellaneous)
  - Miscellaneous bulletins of other associations (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous NCAA (Box 6)
- NCAA
  - Council minutes
    - 1958-1959 (Box 6)
    - 1960 (Box 6)
  - Committee on Recruiting and Financial Aids Papers 1959-1960 (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous 1958-1960 (Box 6)
- Intercollegiate Conference [Big Ten] 1965-1968
  - Papers
    - 1965, undated (Box 6)
    - January-June 1966 (Box 6)
    - July-December 1966 (Box 6)
    - January-June 1967 (Box 6)
    - July-December 1967 (Box 6)
    - 1968 (Box 6)
  - Long-range Thinking Committee, papers 1966 (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
- Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics (U of M) 1941-1968
  As Athletic Director, Crisler served as secretary or chairman of the Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics. The Board in Control series includes correspondence, meeting notes, reports and other material concerning the governance of intercollegiate athletics at Michigan.
  - 1941-1949, undated (Box 6)
  - 1950-1952 (Box 6)
  - 1953-1954 (Box 6)
  - 1955-1957 (Box 6)
  - 1958-1959 (Box 6)
  - 1960 (Box 7)
  - 1961 (Box 7)
  - 1962-1965 (Box 7)
  - 1966-1968 (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
- Scrapbooks and Clippings 1918-1979
  Crisler's personal history can be gleaned from his comprehensive scrapbook collection. The Scrapbooks and Clippings includes both bound volumes and loose clippings covering Crisler's entire career though the bulk of the material covers his years as Michigan football coach.
  - Scrapbooks, 2 volumes (Box 7)
  - Loose Scrapbook material, 4 folders (Box 7)
  - News clippings and articles
    - Brutality in football (Box 7)
    - Princeton 1933 (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
    - 1976 (Box 7)
    - 1977-1979 (Box 7)
  - Scrapbooks
    - 1918-1937 (Volume 1)
    - 1938-1941 (Volume 2)
    - 1942-1946 (Volume 3)
    - 1947-1948 (Volume 4)
    - 1948-1957 (Volume 5)
    - 1958-1973 (Volume 6)
    - 1899-1973 (Volume 7)
- Miscellaneous
  - Papers, 5 folders (Box 7)
  - Programs
    - With articles about Fritz Crisler (Box 7)
    - Containing dedications and honorary induction material (Box 7)
  - Course Book, "The Undergraduate Course Book" University of Chicago 1917 (Box 7)
- Amos Alonzo Stagg
  Crisler's papers also contain material relating to Amos Alonzo Stagg, his football coach and mentor at the University of Chicago. Primarily correspondence with and about Stagg, 1930-1968, the series includes many letters received by Crisler in response to his article on Stagg which appeared in the Readers Digest feature "My Most Unforgettable Character".
  - Correspondence with and about Stagg
    - 1930-1945 (Box 8)
    - 1946-1963, 1968 (Box 8)
    - "My Most Unforgettable Character, " 1963 (Box 8)
  - 1939 NCAA Coach's Convention, Stagg Testimonial, 4 folders
    - Clippings (Box 8)
- Audio-Visual Materials
  The Audio-Visual series includes a single tape of an interview with Crisler, Bump Elliott and Bill Fleming, photographs, a film of the 1948 Rose Bowl Game (also available on videotape) and a film on the History of University of Minnesota football.
  - Audio-Tape (Box 8)
    - Radio Interview with Bump Elliot and Bill Fleming undated (Box 8)
  - Photographs
    The photographs subseries includes images documenting Crisler's career at Michigan and earlier coaching jobs at the universities of Chicago and Minnesota; days as a football, basketball and baseball player at the University of Chicago. There are number of photos of Amos Alonzo Stagg, and Crisler at various professional and social gatherings. The are number of portraits of Crisler and family photos.
    - Early Career (Princeton, Chicago) (Box 8)
    - Family (Box 8)
    - Football players, games, stadia (Box 8)
    - Groups (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 8)
    - Crisler, H.O (Box 8)
    - Stagg, Amos Alonzo 1862-1965 (Box 8)
    - Albums
      - Japanese trip 1920 (Box 8)
      - "C" Chicago men and Stagg reunion, Rose Bowl 1945 (Box 8)
      - Photos and clippings 1899-1931 (Box 8)
    - 1947, undated Photographs (Folder UAm)
  - Films
    - "1948 Rose Bowl Game vs. U.S.C." (Reel 1)
      (also on videotape)
    - "History of Football at The University of Minnesota" (Reel 2)
    - Central Infantry Officers Training School group portrait 1918 (Folder UAl)
Related Materials
A number of collections and archival records at the Bentley Library contain additional documentation relating to Crisler's career as football coach and Athletic Director. Most significant are the Athletic Dept. (University of Michigan) Records and the Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics (University of Michigan) records. The former mainly documents Crisler's work ask football coach while the latter includes administrative files of the Athletic Director's office.